Florian Vichot

Melbourne, Australia
French/Australian citizen
+61 402 936 579
florian.vichot@gmail.com
fvichot fvichot

Principal Site Reliability Engineer

An accomplished software engineer, I have over fifteen years of experience in both development and operations. Well-versed in multiple programming languages, tools and technologies, I'm also a seasoned technical leader and mentor. While mostly drawn to SRE roles, I welcome all opportunities that would allow me to work on challenging and varied problems as part of a talented team. Organisations building open-source software or serving the public interest are especially attractive.

SKILLS

- > Track record of advancing code and infrastructure quality, performance and maintainability
- > Skilled at navigating and mastering complex software codebases
- **>** Dedicated to automate time-consuming and error-prone tasks
- > Experienced in leading teams, acting as technical referent, mentoring other engineers
- > Effective at helping teams plan and prioritise work, negotiating roadmaps with stakeholders
- > Pragmatic approach to complex problems, from tactical short-term goals to long-term strategic vision

EXPERIENCE

Cisco Meraki — Remote, Australia

- Principal Engineer SRE February 2023 to now
 - Acted as **technical advisor** for Platform Engineering, a grouping of 7 SRE teams, by building a shared vision, reviewing solutions, unblocking engineers, initiating workgroups, promoting cross-collaboration.
 - > Mentored several Technical Leads, with weekly one-on-ones with each to discuss technical challenges, career aspirations and leadership development.
 - > Continued to help lead the monolith transition into Kubernetes, by **running sprints**, writing **design docs**, contributing code, reviewing solutions, giving progress demos to stakeholders.
- Senior Technical Leader SRE May 2021 to February 2023
 - > Continued to lead the Kubernetes implementation. Grew it to over 40 clusters worldwide, including AWS China, and FedRAMP-certified clusters. Added support for ArgoCD, ingress-nginx and AWS BYOIP.
 - > Identified a memory leak in the Linux kernel as the source of server crashes using **bpftrace** and the **crash** kernel debugger. Implemented a remediation as a **kernel module**, which over 18 months mitigated over 25,000 leaks, avoiding thousands of server crashes.
 - > Kick-started a **multi-year initiative** to migrate our monolith from bare-metal into Kubernetes, using custom tools and services. Co-lead a squad of engineers to implement an **MVP**.
- Technical Leader SRE March 2019 to May 2021
 - > Led the design and implementation of Meraki's EKS-based **Kubernetes** platform, provisioned using **Terraform** and **Helm**. It included **Grafana** SLO/SLI dashboards, **Fluentd/Kinesis** logging pipeline, **Okta** authentication, **Statsd/Prometheus** metrics collection, **Gitlab** CI deployments, **Kyverno** admission control, strict default **Pod Security Policies** and **Network Policies**.
 - > Designed and implemented a **Haproxy**-based on-prem proxy infrastructure, for exposing customer-facing services running in EKS on IP ranges owned by Meraki. At peak, it was handling 3 million concurrent connections.
 - **> On-call** in a follow-the-sun schedule. Triaged **PagerDuty** alerts, investigated root-causes, deployed remediations or rollbacks, ran post-mortems.

VMTech — Sydney, Australia

- **DevOps Engineer** August 2018 to February 2019
 - > Design and implementation of a customer-facing graphs dashboard, using **Python**, **SQLAlchemy** and **Flask**, using APIs from Splunk, ElasticSearch, ScienceLogic EM7, CommVault and ServiceNow.
 - > Improving automation scripts (a mix of Node.js, Python, Bash) for monthly report generation.

Wifirst — Paris, France

- Infrastructure & Automation Engineer April 2016 to May 2018
 - ➤ Management of over 10,000 Linux routers using Ansible, to provide internet to ~500,000 users.
 - > Developing Python/Bash services to configure iptables, routes, and supervision on Linux routers.
 - > Designing and evolving our monitoring infrastructure for a large volume of data (150,000 devices supervised) using Python, Nginx, Django, PostgreSQL, Redis.
 - > Writing code to configure various network equipment: Cisco, Zyxel, DLink.
 - > Speaker at PyCon France 2017.

Inria, Asclepios Lab — Sophia-Antipolis, France

- Senior Software Engineer March 2012 to April 2015
 - ➤ Lead developer on medInria, a C++/Qt open-source medical image visualisation, processing and manipulation software, to add cardiac related functionalities.
 - > Setup CI/CD using Jenkins, to test and build software on Debian, Fedora, OSX and Windows 7+.
 - > Improved the reliability of medInria and its code quality by instituting code-reviews and a pull-request based workflow. Migrated the project to **GitHub**, reorganised, cleaned and simplified the source code, re-architected and updated the build/test system.
 - > Evolved medInria's architecture to handle new functionalities, and transformed it into a framework for other projects using a plugin system.
 - > Attended and presented at conferences (MICCAI), workshops (CTK), and contributed to scientific articles.

Telecoms Without Borders — Pau, France

- Systems & Network Engineer Sept. 2010 to Oct. 2011, April 2015
 - > Deployed on various international missions in response to humanitarian emergencies: floods, influx of refugees, cyclone, conflict or famine, for a total of 5 months on mission. Established telephone operations for populations, installed **network and satellite equipment** for NGOs and the UN. Provided trainings.
 - > Maintained and evolved the NGO's infrastructure (website, email servers, storage server, equipment database, OpenBSD firewall).
 - > Contributed to the TSFBox, a custom **Linux** router facilitating monitoring and optimization of internet connections provided during missions, with services written in **Perl**.

Diateam — Brest, France

- Software Engineer June 2008 to April 2010, July/August 2007
 - > Implemented a multithread RPC framework in C++/Qt4, and its code generator and test suite.
 - > Lead developer on the Hynesim open source project (Hybrid Network Simulator): implementation in C++/Qt4 of virtual network components, custom GUI widget and of wrappers around different virtualization technologies (OpenVZ/LXC containers, Qemu/KVM VMs) using livbirt. Speaker for conferences at OSSIRB and Hack.lu 2008.
 - > Contributor to IpMorph: **TCP/IP stack** fingerprint spoofing for **containers** and **VMs**. Speaker during Hack.lu 2009. Co-authored a publication.

EDUCATION

> ENIB, National Engineering School of Brest, France from 2003 to 2008 (Master's Degree in Engineering).

PUBLICATIONS

Cardiac Interventional Guidance using Multimodal Data Processing and Visualisation: medInria as an Interoperability Platform — Midas Journal — 2012

Authors: F. Vichot, H. Cochet, B. Bleuzé, N. Toussaint, P. Jaïs, M. Sermesant

MedInria is a medical imaging application developed at Inria, which aims to provide clinicians with state-of-the-art algorithms for processing and visualising their images. In this article, we focus on its use in presurgery preparation for cardiac interventions, and the difficulties arising from the lack of standardisation of certain data formats and visualisation conventions.

IpMorph: fingerprinting spoofing unification — Journal in computer virology 6, no. 4 — 2010 Authors: G. Prigent, F. Vichot, F. Harrouet

Nowadays, there are a variety of tools for easily identifying the TCP/IP stack's fingerprint of a target machine. IpMorph allows this fingerprint to be concealed, and even mimicks the fingerprint of a chosen TCP/IP stack. This is done through live session tracking and packet rewriting. Its effectiveness against tools such as Nmap, Xprobe2, Ring2, SinFP and p0f is also detailed.